<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>About</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                        <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                        <surname>Hannesschl채ger</surname>
                    </persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>ACDH-OeAW</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
                <date when="2017"/>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>The Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) License applies
                            to this text.</p>
                        <p>The CC BY 4.0 License also applies to this TEI XML file.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>born digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>About this website</head>
                <p>This website is part of the <ref target="https://acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</ref>' efforts to document the TEI Conference and Members' Meeting 2016 (visit the <ref target="http://tei2016.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/">conference website</ref>), which was hosted by the Centre at the <ref target="http://www.oeaw.ac.at/">Austrian Academy of Sciences</ref> in Vienna, with a digital humanities-comformant approach.</p>
                <p>This website was created by Peter Andorfer with the support of Vanessa Hannesschl채ger in order to provide a user-friendly interface for the XML/TEI versions of the abstracts of the TEI Conference and Members' Meeting 2016 as well as several visualisations of the data the abstracts came with. These files were provided by Vanessa Hannesschl채ger and Daniel Schopper and are available on <ref target="https://github.com/acdh-oeaw/TEI2016abstracts/tree/master/TEI">GitHub</ref>. They were created from the original printed Book of Abstracts (see the <ref target="http://tei2016.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/sites/default/files/TEIconf2016_BookOfAbstracts.pdf">PDF</ref>), which was edited by Claudia Resch, Vanessa Hannesschl채ger and Tanja Wissik. The application architecture, layout and core functionalities are based on <ref target="https://github.com/acdh-oeaw/generic-de-web-app">generic-de-web-app</ref>. Please refer to <ref target="https://howto.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/blog/books/how-to-build-a-digital-edition-web-app/">How to build a digital edition web app</ref> for further information.</p>
                <p>If you come across any mistakes or wish to edit the data we provide, please do! The code is open source and freely available on <ref target="https://github.com/acdh-oeaw/tei-abstracts-app">GitHub</ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>